Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in The Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in The Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens
N/A
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892
poetry manuscripts prose
Department of Manuscripts The Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens 1151 Oxford Road San Marino, California 91108
This electronic catalog was created from the original catalog records obtained by The Walt Whitman Archive. The original papers and catalog records are held at The Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens.
Restrictions on Original Materials:
Please consult with repository.
Scope and Content
The Huntington's Department of Manuscripts holds numerous Whitman items, including drafts of poetry and prose, correspondence, notebooks, and pieces about Whitman by other authors. For this catalog, only those objects deemed poetry or prose manuscripts have been described at the item-level.
Biographical Information
Subjects
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892--Manuscripts; Poets, American--19th century
Item List
- Beginners, about 1860; hun.00006; xxx.00034; HM 11202; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Complete draft, lightly revised, of Beginners, a poem first published in Leaves of Grass ( 1860–61 ) and reprinted in all subsequent editons.
- The dead in this war [Write a piece for address], between 1864 and 1875; hun.00019; xxx.00926; HM 1194; prose 2 leaves handwritten
  Notes about death during the U.S. Civil War, apparently intended for a projected lecture that never materialized. Whitman used these notes for the short essay The Million Dead, too, summ'd up—The Unknown, which was first published in Memoranda During the War ( 1875–76 ).
- 'Come said my soul.. .' [Come, said my Soul], about 1875; hun.00021; xxx.00596; HM 6713; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A signed draft, heavily revised, of the untitled poem that Whitman used for some printings of Leaves of Grass, beginning in 1876. It was first published as part of A Christmas Garland in Prose and Verse in the New York Daily Graphic of December 25, 1874. The date in the poet's note at the top suggests that this manuscript might represent a revision stage later than the poem's initial publication.
- Fancies at Navesink, the Pilot in the mist Fancies at Navesink, about 1885; hun.00014; xxx.00331; xxx.00330; HM 1190; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A draft of Pilot in the Mist, the first in the eight-poem sequence Fancies at Navesink, first published in the August 1885 issue of Nineteenth Century. On the verso is a letter dated October 3, 1884 to Whitman from Richard Hines requesting information about Martin Farquhar Tupper.
- Longings for home Longings for Home, about 1860; hun.00001; xxx.00274; HM 11200; poetry 5 leaves handwritten
  Lightly revised draft of a poem first published as Longings For Home in Southern Literary Messenger ( July 1860 ) and Leaves of Grass ( 1860–61 ). It was reprinted in Leaves of Grass ( 1871–72 ). In later editions it appeared under the title O Magnet-South, with minor revisions.
- [Leaves of grass] You Lingering Sparse Leaves of Me, May 1885; hun.00015; xxx.00368; HM 1193; poetry 1 leaf proof with handwritten corrections and annotations
  Corrected proof sheet for the poem You Lingering Sparse Leaves of Me, dated May 1885. The poem was first published in the November 1887 issue of Lippincott's Magazine in a collection of four poems titled November Boughs. It was reprinted in Leaves of Grass ( 1891-1892 ).
- [Leaves of grass] You Lingering Sparse Leaves of Me, between 1885 and 1887; hun.00017; xxx.00368; HM 1193; poetry 1 leaf proof with handwritten annotations
  Corrected proof sheet for the poem You Lingering Sparse Leaves of Me, which was first published in the November 1887 issue of Lippincott's Magazine in a collection of four poems titled November Boughs. It was reprinted in Leaves of Grass ( 1891-1892 ).
- The singer in the prison The Singer in the Prison, about 1869; hun.00010; xxx.00233; HM 11206; poetry 4 leaves handwritten
  This is draft of The Singer in the Prison, a poem first published in December 25, 1869 issue of Saturday Evening Visitor with the subtitle A Christmas Incident. Whitman included it, without subtitle, in the Leaves of Grass cluster of Passage to India (1871). Finally, in the 1881–82 edition it became part of the Autumn Rivulets cluster.
- [I for the old round earth] Preface to Leaves of Grass, 1863-1867; hun.00022; xxx.00005; xxx.00953; HM 6714; poetry 2 leaves handwritten
  Although the repository labels this manuscript as a draft of the Preface to the 1855 Leaves of Grass, it appears to have been written in the mid-1860s and was potentially intended as the opening inscription to the 1867 edition of Leaves (Whitman has written "Inscription, to precede Leaves of Grass, when finished" at the top of the first leaf). While the poem in this form was never published, the line describing the Greek god Kronos as "brown-skinned" may have led to a similar description in Chanting the Square Deific, which first appeared in Sequel to Drum-Taps in 1865.
- [While the schools] Preface to Leaves of Grass, between 1863 and 1867; hun.00066; xxx.00954; HM 6714; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Although the repository groups this manuscript with two other leaves and ties them all to the 1855 Preface to Leaves of Grass, it appears that this is a separate manuscript and that none of them are related to the 1855 Preface. This manuscript was likely written in the mid-1860s and was never published.
- Soon shall the winter's foil be here, about 1888; hun.00016; xxx.00360; HM 1192; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Heavily corrected draft of Soon Shall the Winter's Foil Be Here, a poem published first in the New York Herald on February 21, 1888. It was reprinted in November Boughs (1888) and Leaves of Grass (1891–92), where it appeared in the Sands at Seventy cluster.
- Tests, ca. 1860; hun.00007; xxx.00251; HM 11203; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Draft, with a few corrections, of Tests, a poem published first in Leaves of Grass (1860–61) and reprinted in subsequent editions.
- To the Future To a common prostitute, about 1860; hun.00008; xxx.00294; xxx.00951; HM 11205; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Draft of a poem titled To the Future. Although the poem was unpublished in its entirety, the seventh line was used in the poem To My Soul, which was first published in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass and later retitled As the Time Draws Nigh. On the reverse is a draft of To a Common Prostitute.
- To a Common Prostitute To a common prostitute, about 1860; hun.00065; xxx.00261; HM 11205; poetry 1leaf handwritten
  Draft of To a Common Prostitute, a poem published first in the 1860–61 edition of Leaves of Grass and retained in all subsequent editions. On the verso is a draft of an unpublished poem entitled To the Future.
- Thoughts, about 1860; hun.00002; xxx.00413; HM 11201; poetry 3 leaves handwritten
  Draft, with minor corrections, of the first poem in the cluster titled Thoughts when it was first published in Leaves of Grass ( 1860–61 ). It was reprinted in the 1867 edition of Leaves of Grass but omitted from all subsequent editions.
- 6 Thoughts, about 1860; hun.00003; xxx.00413; HM 11201; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Draft, with a few corrections, of the sixth poem in the cluster titled Thoughts when it was first published in Leaves of Grass ( 1860–61 ). In the 1867 edition it appeared again as 6 in the Thoughts cluster. In the 1871–72 edition, revised and titled Thought, it was included in the Songs of Parting cluster. It did not appear in later editions of Leaves of Grass.
- Thoughts, about 1860; hun.00004; xxx.00413; HM 11201; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Draft, with revisions, of the seventh poem in the cluster titled Thoughts when it was first published in Leaves of Grass ( 1860–61 ). In the 1867 edition it appeared again as 7 in the Thoughts cluster. In the 1871–72 edition it was titled Thought and not included in any cluster. Finally, in Leaves of Grass (1881–82) it appeared as Thought in the By the Roadside cluster.
- 2 Thoughts, about 1860; hun.00005; xxx.00413; HM 11201; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Draft, with minor revisions, of the second poem in the cluster titled Thoughts when it was first published in Leaves of Grass ( 1860–61 ). In the 1867 and 1871–72 editions it appeared again as 2 in clusters titled Thoughts. Finally, in Leaves of Grass (1881–82) Whitman combined parts of this and another poem, again titled Thoughts, and included it in the By the Roadside cluster.
- Queries To My Seventieth Year To my seventieth year, 1888; hun.00011; xxx.00320; HM 11207; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Heavily revised draft, signed, of Queries to My Seventieth Year, a poem first published in the May 2, 1888 issue of the New York Herald. It was reprinted in November Boughs (1888) and included in the Sands at Seventy annex of Leaves of Grass ( 1891–92 ).
- To Him that was Crucified To him that was crucified, about 1860; hun.00013; xxx.00238; HM 11208; poetry 3 leaves handwritten
  Draft, with many corrections, of To Him That Was Crucified, a poem first published in Leaves of Grass ( 1860–61 ).
- A Twilight Song, about 1890; hun.00020; xxx.00398; HM 1224; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Late draft, with a few corrections, of A Twilight Song, a poem first published in the May 1890 issue of Century Illustrated Monthly Magazine, where it was subtitled For unknown buried soldiers, North and South. It was reprinted, without the subtitle, in Good-Bye My Fancy (1891) and in the Good-By my Fancy annex of Leaves of Grass (1891–92).
- To Other Lands To other lands, about 1860; hun.00009; xxx.00027; HM 11204; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Draft, with some corrections, of the poem eventually titled To Foreign Lands, first published in Leaves of Grass ( 1860–61 ) as To other Lands as part of the Messenger Leaves cluster. In the 1871–72 edition it received its final title and position within the Inscriptions cluster.
- Bed 37, 1863; hun.00027; xxx.00502; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Notes made about a visit to Armory Square Hospital in Washington, D.C. in 1863. Revised versions of these lines were published in 'Tis But Ten Years Since (Fourth Paper), the fourth of six articles about the Civil War that Whitman published in the New York Weekly Graphic in January and February, 1874. The fourth number appeared on 21 February 1874. The articles were later gathered and republished as Memoranda During the War in 1875.
- Carlyle from American points of View Carlyle from American points of view, 1882; hun.00034; xxx.00828; HM 138; prose 37 leaves handwritten
  A draft of Whitman's essay Carlyle from American Points of View, first published in Specimen Days in 1882. At the top of the draft, Whitman indicates that the piece was originally submitted for publication in the North American Review on 20 May 1882, but was rejected.
- Authors at Home - No. VII Walt Whitman at Camden, 1885; hun.00039; xxx.00829; HM 1196; prose 9 leaves handwritten
  Draft of an article entitled Walt Whitman in Camden that Whitman published pseudonymously in The Critic on 25 February 1885. The article, published under the name "George Selwyn," was part of a series called "American Authors at Home" that ran for several volumes in 1885. The article would later be reprinted by The Critic Co. in 1898 as a separate pamphlet entitled Walt Whitman at Home, which credited Whitman as the author of the piece.
- [Walt Whitman said lately to one of his interviewers], 1886; hun.00036; xxx.00830; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A manuscript written by Whitman and sent to William Sloane Kennedy, most likely in 1886. Kennedy would use the manuscript, along with several others, in an article entitled Dutch Traits of Walt Whitman which appeared under Kennedy's name in In Re Walt Whitman in 1893, a volume edited by Horace Traubel, Richard Maurice Bucke, and Thomas Harned, Whitman's literary executors. It is likely Kennedy's handwriting that appears in dark pencil on the verso.
- [Going back far enough], 1886; hun.00064; xxx.00830; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A manuscript written by Whitman and sent to William Sloane Kennedy, most likely in 1886. Kennedy would use the manuscript, along with several others, in an article entitled Dutch Traits of Walt Whitman which appeared under Kennedy's name in In Re Walt Whitman in 1893, a volume edited by Horace Traubel, Richard Maurice Bucke, and Thomas Harned, Whitman's literary executors. On the verso is a portion of a letter to Whitman from W.E. Mitchell.
- Lafayette in Brooklyn Account of the visit of Lafayette to Brooklyn in 1825, 1881; hun.00037; xxx.00831; HM 1189; prose 6 leaves handwritten
  A manuscript containing the text of a address that Whitman purportedly gave at the New England Historic Genealogical Society in Boston, likely on 7 October 1881 (see Edward Grier, Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts [New York: New York University Press, 1984] 1:32).
- [Most all of the wounds very bad] Notes on hospital experiences, 1862-1874; hun.00041; xxx.00502; HM 6708; prose 4 leaves handwritten
  A manuscript describing Whitman's time spent in the army camps and hospitals near Fredericksburg in late December, 1862. The manuscripts are fairly neat and on the verso on the fourth leaf Whitman has written "Proofs," indicating that these were likely handwritten proofs for one of the several newspaper articles that Whitman published about these experiences, articles that would later be incorporated into Memoranda During the War. Some of the lines here first appeared in Our Wounded and Sick Soldiers, published in the New York Times on 11 December 1864, and were later reprinted in a series of articles written for the New York Weekly Graphic in 1874.
- Father Taylor (and Oratory) Father Taylor (and Oratory), 1886-1887; hun.00044; xxx.00463; HM 6711; prose 11 leaves handwritten
  Late-stage draft (with printer's instructions) of the essay Father Taylor (and Oratory), which first appeared in Century Magazine in February 1887. The piece would later be reprinted in November Boughs. Edward Thompson Taylor was a Boston Methodist minister known for his powerful sermons, serving as the inspiration for Melville's "Father Mapple" in Moby Dick. Whitman went to hear Taylor speak on several occassions during his stay in Boston in 1860.
- A Thought on Shakspere A Thought on Shakespeare, 1881-1886; hun.00045; xxx.00466; HM 6712; prose 6 leaves handwritten
  A fairly late draft of the essay A Thought on Shakspere, which first appeared in The Critic on 14 August 1886. It would later be reprinted in Democratic Vistas, and Other Papers ( 1888 ) and again in November Boughs.
- [in life] [Memoranda During the War], 1873-1875; hun.00051; xxx.00502; HM 16537; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A manuscript fragment that, on the recto, contains lines similar to those found in the opening paragraph of Memoranda During the War ( 1875 ), and may have been an alternate or earlier version of that introduction. The paragraph first appeared in a slightly different form in the New York Weekly Graphic on 24 January 1874, part of a five-part series about the war that Whitman published in that paper. The verso contains lines which appear in the final paragraph of Whitman's introduction to Memoranda, and were likely written later than the lines on the recto.
- Old Poets Old Poets: [essay], 1890; hun.00053; xxx.00559; HM 50563; prose 2 leaves handwritten
  A draft of Whitman's essay Old Poets, with handwritten printer's instructions at the top of the first leaf. The essay was first printed in the North American Review in November 1890 and later reprinted in the Pall Mall Gazette ( 17 November 1890 ) and in Good-Bye My Fancy ( 1891 ).
- [Reminiscences], 1864-1865; hun.00033; xxx.00217; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A manuscript fragment containing what appear to be poetic lines written about the dead of the Civil War, and which are included at the Huntington Library with a group of notes labeled "Hospital Notes 1863." Edward Grier suggests that these lines may have been for an early version of a lecture that Whitman intended to give on The Dead in this War. The lines also anticipate portions of When Lilacs Last in the Dooryard Bloom'd. The manuscript is labeled "Reminiscences 64" at the top.
- A Visit to the Opera A visit to the opera, 1855-1860; hun.00038; xxx.00908; xxx.00909; HM 1191; prose 8 leaves handwritten
  A fairly neat draft of what appears to be a piece of journalism that was never published. Entitled (by Whitman) A Visit to the Opera, the draft bears many similarities to a piece that Whitman published in Life Illustrated on November 10, 1855, entitled The Opera. It is likely that this draft is a revision of that earlier piece, intended for subsequent publication in a different periodical. Whitman has numbered the pages, but pages 8 and 9 are missing. Whitman signs the draft "Mose Velsor, of Brooklyn," one of his commonly-used pseudonyms. For more discussion of this draft's relation to The Opera, and to several other manuscripts, see: Edward Grier, Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts (New York: New York Univeristy Press, 1984) 1:388-397.